Guide to the Stanford University, Department of History, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of History, records
1903-1974
SC0029A
Stanford University. Department of History.
18 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer
Information about Access
Boxes 16 through 21 are restricted; consult the University Archivist for access.
Scope and Content
The files of the History Department are diverse and fairly complete and include correspondence, minutes, memoranda, course materials, enrollment records, and reports. A few of the subjects covered by the records are: establishment of the Political Science Department; report on the four-quarter system; History Club minutes; course offerings including those taught in both World Wars; the Army Specialized Training Program of 1941-1945; Independent Study; Problems of Citizenship; Western Civilization; international relations committees; and university-wide committees on faculty self-discipline and general studies. There is also a manuscript History of the History Department.
Boxes 1 through 9 were transferred to the Archives in 1966; a folder by folder survey of the papers was made but only names of important personalities were recorded. Boxes 10 through 21 were transferred to the Archives in August 1975. Boxes 10-15 contain the files of Prof. Gordon Craig; in boxes 16-21 the name of the department chairman or faculty member who created the file, where it can be determined, has been included in brackets after the folder title. Boxes 16 through 21 are restricted; please consult the University Archivist for access. Two letters dated 1903 from Max Farrand (then Dept. head) to Henry Cannon, describing the methods of running classes and department affairs, were given to the Archives in November 1970 by Mrs. Leland Brown.
This collection complements the Edgar E. Robinson Papers which were received in 1964. For a complete history of the History Department of Leland Stanford Junior University consultation of the Robinson Papers is essential.
Collection Contents
- General Correspondence, 1903-1961
  - 2 letters. Max Farrand to Henry Cannon, 1903 (Box 1, Folder A)
  - A, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    H. Cannon, H.E. Bolton, D.S. Jordan, E.D. Adams F.P. Reppel (of the Association for International Conciliation).
    Correspondence is primarily between Adams and Bolton and deals with Stanford's hiring of the latter.
  - B, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    H. Cannon, H. Bolton, J. Branner, John Baer, J. Bowman (of U.C.), George Burr, John Blair, James Breakey.
  - C, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    G.E. Clark (Univ. librarian), chiefly concerning acquisition of books.
  - D, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    C.A. Duniway (concerning Pacific Coast Branch of the AHA), W. Dunning (of Columbia Univ.), Harvey Dorr (grad ass't).
  - E, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    O.L. Elliott (Univ. Registrar).
  - F, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    G.F. Foster, Max Farrand, H. Fairclough.
  - G-H, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    H.C. Hoover, sheet giving information about men in the History Department, list of history courses and attendence 1907-08, Charles Hull.
  - I-J, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    D.S. Jordan (Chiefly business letters between Jordan and Adams. Topics include recommendation of E.B. Krehbiel, Dr. Treat's behavior, J.F. Jameson, book import tax, S.L. Ware, Committee on Athletics, P. Martin, E.B. Krehbiel, George A. Burr, H.E. Bolton, Library).
  - K, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    E.B. Krehbiel, J.F. Kenney.
  - L, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Charles Lathrop
  - M, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    J.E. Matzke, S.T. Murray, J. Macy (extensive correspondence dealing with hiring), Percy Martin, W.E. Martin.
  - N-O, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    H.W. Ostroski.
  - P-Q, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Fredrick L. Paxson, material dealing with preliminary papers.
  - R, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    John J. Ryan.
  - S, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    John Stillman, Donald Smith (U.C.), Theodore C. Smith, H.M. Stephens.
  - T, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    P.J. Treat, F.J. Turner, F.J. Teggart, number of telegrams dealing specially with the hiring of H.E. Bolton.
  - U-V-W, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    J.A. Woodburn, Jeanne E. Wier.
  - X-Z, 1908-09 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    A.A. Young.
  - A-B, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    C.M. Andrews, J.N. Bowman.
  - C, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    H.L. Cannon, G.T. Clark, G.A. Clark, G.E. Crothers.
  - D, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    C.A. Duniway.
  - E-G, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    O.L. Elliott, degree requirements for economics/sociology.
  - H-J, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Charles H. Hull, D.S. Jordan, J.F. Jameson, J.P. Hemphill, Jarboe Collection (acquisition).
  - K-M, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Burt O. Kinney, A.C. McLaughlin, A.T. Murray, Jesse Macy.
  - N-R, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    F.L. Paxson, library business, programs for meeting of Pacific Coast Branch of AHA.
  - S-V, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Don E. Smith, F.J. Teggart.
  - W-Z, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Woodrow Wilson, numerous letters concerning S.L. Ware, extensive correspondence between Adams and Mary Williams, J.A. Woodburn.
  - A-B, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    John Branner, J. Bowman.
  - C, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    H.L. Cannon, recommendations for E.E. Robinson, I.J. Cox (especially dealing with American invasion of West Florida), E.P. Cubberley, G.A. Clark, G.T. Clark.
  - D-G, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    W.A. Dunning, Max Farrand, Edw. Elliott's recommendation of E.E. Robinson, E.C. Franklin, A.L. Guerard, F.A. Golder.
  - H-J, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    D.S. Jordan, letters concerning acquisition of Archives Parlementaires, letter concerning the hiring of E.E. Robinson, British Sessional Papers.
  - K-M, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Letters about E.E. Robinson.
  - N-R, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    F. Paxson, E.E. Robinson.
  - S-V, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    F.J. Turner, acquisition of Reichstag reports from Germany.
  - W-Z, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    G. Hempl, R. Wenley, J.E. Wier, Mary Williams.
  - A-B, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    John Branner, H.E. Bolton.
  - C, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Smyth Collection, I.J. Cox.
  - D-F, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Max Farrand.
  - G-J, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    D.S. Jordan, acquisition of H.C. Hoover's Chinese Collection, H.C. Hoover, J.F. Jameson, A.B. Hurlburt.
  - K-L, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - M-Q, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - R-V, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    J.M. Vincent.
  - W-Z, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Mary Williams, R. Wenley.
  - A-B, 1912-13 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - C-D, 1912-13 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    H.C. Cannon, C.A. Duniway.
  - E-G, 1912-13 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    H.R. Fairclough, O.L. Elliott.
  - H, 1912-13 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Annual report (essentially same as in the President's Report, but includes items such as gift sources and several minor items not included in the Report), D.S. Jordan, AHA, letters concerning Adams' leave of absence, R.F. Howes, V.L. Kellogg, letters resulting from visit of Oliviera Lima.
  - N-Z, 1912-13 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    A.B. Show, letters dealing with interdepartmental theses, R.L. Wilbur, Mary Williams.
  - A-J (from this point on, folders are sorted roughly by alphabetical groups and chronologically within these), 1913-14 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Mary Williams, rough draft of material for presidential report, E.B. Krehbiel, John Branner (especially with regard to establishment of a political science department), Adams' leave of absence, G.T. Clark, Max Farrand, P.J. Treat, Yamato Ichihashi (and letters concerning him).
  - K-Z, 1913-14 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    P.A. Martin, E.E. Robinson, H.M. Stephens, P.J. Treat (including letters concerning Ichihashi), M.S. Wildman, F.C. Woodward.
  - A-Z, 1914-15 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Comments on Vega collection of letters and documents, Preparation for Journalism, A.C. Coolidge, G.S. Ford (letters concerning E.E. Robinson), W.S. Ferguson (letters concerning F.A. Golder F.H. Hodder, C.T. Lapsley, I.F. Lange, Ralph Lutz, C.H. Levermore (World Peace Foundation), A. Kline, T.M. Marshall, T.P. Martin, P.A. Martin, T.R. Root, American Society of International Law, J.E. Wier, formation of History Club, History Club minutes.
  - A-Z, 1915-16 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    John Branner, preliminary material for presidential report, J.W. Baer, G.T. Robinson, death of Dr. Blair, E.C. Franklin, Y. Ichihashi, T.S. Kuykendall E.B. Krehbiel, W.A. Morris, AHA business, letters (to C.E. Nelson) on consular and diplomatic training, I.M. Patrick (son of Gen. Patrick), E. E. Robinson, Spalding Collection of baseball, History Club, letters concerning French War cartoons, R.L. Wilbur (especially concerning Ichihashi), Plan for Limitation of Students and Stanford University, establishment of political science department, Committee on Vocational Guidance, J.H. Meyer endowment, letter concerning Mary Williams, History Club minutes.
  - 1916-17 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    H.E. Bolton, Committee on Vocational Guidance, J.H. Meyer endowment, letter concerning Mary Williams, Dr. F.A. Hassler's maps, Report of the Department Committee on the Four-Quarter System, E.B. Krehbiel, W.G. Leland, R. Lutz, William MacDonald, W.A. Morris, Professor Emerton's proposed visit, Geroid Robinson, A.B. Show, J.M. Stillman, H. Suzzallo, J.B. Scott (Director, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace), Sutro Branch (Calif. State Library), preliminary material for the presidential report, R.L. Wilbur, Seabury Fellowship, material concerning Y. Ichihashi, letters concerning re-appointment of H. Cannon and E.E. Robinson.
  - 10/1917 - 4/1919 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Letters seeking replacement for Cannon, American Peace Society, Jens Bugge, Vocational Guidance Committee, NAACP, W.A. Dunning (especially with regard to establishment of political science department), C.A. Fryer, E.M. Hulme, British Documents, Charles W. Hackett, A.M. Kline, E.B. Krehbiel, Seaman's Church Institute (solicitations), World Peace Foundation pamphlet mailing list, P.A. Martin (also concerning Doheny Research Foundation), War History Committee, T.M. Marshall, William A. Morris, C.D. Marx, W. Notestein, I.M. Patrick, plans for Stanford War History, E.E. Robinson, Borel Fund, A.B. Show, J.M. Stillman, H.M. Stephens, P.J. Treat, R.L. Wilbur (also concerning establishment of political science department), Committee of 15.
  - 4/1919 - 12/1919 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Brazilian Library, Y. Ichihashi, P.A. Martin, R. Lutz, E.E. Robinson, J.F. Jameson, T.M. Marshall W.A. Morris, F.M. Russell, E. Krehbiel, Committees for Educational Preparation for Foreign Service, Joseph Schafer, J.W. Swain, P.J. Treat, R.G. Trotte R.L. Wilbur.
  - 1920 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    A.H. Abbott, E.F. Albertsworth, Walter Barnes, E.S. Brown, G. Burr, H.E. Bolton, J.A. Blaisdell, C.J. Brosnan, sabbatical leave, M.W. Graham, F.A. Golder, C.H. Haskins, E.M. Hulme, H.B. Learned, K.C. Leebrick, R.H. Lutz, E. Krehbiel, E.E. Robinson, C. Robinson, A.B. Show, J. Van Nostrand, W. Westergaard, Seabury Scholarship, A.C. Olney (recommendation for W. Westergaard).
  - 1921 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Edward Beach (proposed American naval history lectures), Sydney M. Brown, F.A. Golder, E.A. Horne E.M. Hulme, E.E. Robinson, H.B. Learned, A.M. Kline T.M. Marshall, M.W. Graham, C.H. Van Tyne, H.E. Wildes, W. Westergaard, establishment of Mabel H. Cory Scholarship.
  - 1/1922 - 9/1922 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Adams Private Lecture Series, F.L. Beach, W.C. Barnes, E.S. Brown, H. Hoover (Secretary of Commerce), D.S. Jordan, R.H. Leach, Charles R. Hicks, L.V. Koos, H.B. Learned, T.P. Martin, New York Council for Limitation of Armaments, Data for presidential report, I.M. Patrick, G.T. Robinson, F.M. Russell, B. E. Schmitt, C. Seymour, H.E. Wildes, R.L. Wilbur, Brazilian Library.
  - 1928-29 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Carnegie Institute of Washington (Department of Historical Research), A.M. Kline, C.A. Duniway, H.C. Crockett, Independent Study Plan, P.J. Treat, H.G. Warren, W.C. Barnes, P.A. Martin (acting executive head), Institute of International Education, C.W. Hackett, R. Lutz, H. Temperley, R.L. Wilbur, C.E.E.B., T. Bailey.
  - Professor Robinson's File, 1929-30 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    J.E.W. Sterling, H.G. Warren, E.D. Adams, R.C. Binkley, W.C. Barnes, C.R. Fish, J. Ellison, H.H. Fisher, L.A. Harper, D. Harris, C.W. Hackett, C.B. Malone, P.A. Martin, Wallace Notestein, Frederick Moore, W.H. Robson, AHA, J.W. Thompson, Ray Turner.
  - F.A. Golder's Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 61)
    R.F. Arragon, Albert Guerard (involved with international language), R.H. Lord, O.H. Wedel.
  - 1930-31 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    E.D. Adams, Robert Binkley; also includes one or two items from 1926.
  - 1930-31 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Death of E.D. Adams, P.B. Albright, C.B. Malone material for presidential report, appointment of Thomas Bailey, Oregon Trail Memorial Association, G. Vernadsky.
  - 10/1931 - 10/1932 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    W.F. Adams, independent study, material for President's Report, J.E.W. Sterling, Max Savelle, P. J. Treat.
  - 9/1932 - 8/1933 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Letters discussing organization of history courses, material for President's Report, J.A. Barnes, R.H. Lutz, Max Savelle.
  - 1933-34 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    Memoranda (etc.) from E.E. Robinson, faculty research projects, History Club constitution, material for President's Report.
  - 1934-35 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    H.A. DeWeerd, C.N. Spinks, H.N.M. Winton, E.M. Hulme, material for President's Report, Emergency Relief Administration (especially with regard to student employment), question of preregistration.
  - 1935-37 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - General, 1935-36
      Max Savelle (conflict with Van Patten), Calif. Youth Administration (student employment), P.A. Martin, H.F. Taggart, H.W. Temperley.
    - E.E. Robinson, 1935-36
      R.C. Binkley, Leonard Ferguson, Ralph Gabriel, Gordon Wright, J.P. Moore, W. Westergaard.
    - General (1), 1936-37
      T.A. Bailey, F.G. Graham, Lynn White.
    - General (2), 1936-37
      Max Savelle (Western Civilization questionnaire and extensive report), Henry M. Madden, assorted departmental information regarding enrollment, independent study and interdepartmental majors (Harris-Robinson), Harold Temperley, H.H. Fisher (Hoover Institute policies), comments on Far Eastern history program, Ernest C. Arbuckle (value of history major), Memorandum on the Work of the Department of History, P.A. Martin, committee considering departmental offerings and schedule.
    - Lynn White Correspondence, 1936-37
    - E.E. Robinson, 1936-37
      T.A. Bailey, S.F. Bemis, Paul Eckel, W.S. Thompson, John Gange, P.A. Martin, R.E. Albright, C.M. Spinks, Tokyo meeting of World Federation of Education Associations, H.G. Warren, R.L. Wilbur, Harry Winton, Gordon Wright.
  - 1937-40 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - 1937-38
      C.A. Barker, Charles Scott, E.A. Cottrell (with regard to certain department policies concerning graduate students, etc.), letter to Mrs. Benjamin Harrison, E.R. Hilgard, Ralph Lutz, P.A. Martin, P.J. Treat.
    - 1938-39
      AHA, S.F. Bemis, D.H. Burney, M. Cardozo, G.W. Cottrell, English-Speaking Union, A.C.Krey, C.F. Brand, Beverly McAnear, F.L. Paxson, AHA, C.N. Spinks, Dr. Pardee's California Papers, Lynn White, Dorothea Wyatt.
    - 1939-40
      T.A. Bailey, H.K. Beale, Max Savelle, H.H. Fisher, P.A. Martin, T. Mitchell, H.M. Smith, Nelson Spinks, H.G. Warren.
  - 1940-45 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - General, 1940-41
      C.F. Brand, T.A. Bailey, Chester Davis (old Calif. letters), John Gange, David Harris, E.M. Hulme, R. Lutz, P.A. Martin, D.T. Moorhead, M. Spalding, Establishment of the School of Humanities
    - General, 1941-42
      David Harris, E.M. Hulme, R. Lutz, W.H. Dusenberry, death of P.A. Martin.
    - Selective Service correspondence, 1941-45
  - 1942-45 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - 1942-43
      R. Lutz, H.H. Fisher, T.A. Bailey, B. Schilling of Grinnell College, C.F. Brand, A.D. Mazour, letters containing suggestions for departmental policies (by Bailey, Savelle and others).
    - 1943-44
      T.A. Bailey, George Knoles, Donald B. Tresidder, H.H. Fisher.
    - 1944-45
      M. Cameron (problem of disciplining Army trainees), C.C. Griffen, D. Harris, R. Lutz, M. Savelle, R.K. Snyder, M. Spalding, Shelby F. Strother, John Vanderburgh.
  - 1945-46 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    (autumn): C. Barker, Harlan R. Crippen, R.J. Kerner, A.C. Krey, H.F. McCreery, Harlan Notter (Rosenberg Foundation), Max Savelle, R.K. Snyder, H.F. Taggart Borel Collection, H.N.M. Winton.
    (winter, spring, summer): William D. Beatty, Carl F. Brand, T.A. Bailey, H.H. Fisher, Norman A. Graebner, Norman S. Kelley, R. Lutz, B. McAnear, C.E. Nowell, M. Savelle, E.D. Sohm, W.W. Tinsley, P.J. Treat, Owen Ulph, John A. White.
  - 1946-47 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    A. Bestor, M. Cameron, E.M. Hulme, Bruce Mazlish A. Mazour, Fredrick Merk, D. Moorhead, F.L. Paxson.
  - 1947-48 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    (summer): T.A. Bailey, W.C. Bark, C.A. Buss, A. Guerard, D. Phillips.
    (autumn, winter): T.A. Bailey, T.C. Smith, H. Holloorn, A. Hyma, L.K. Koontz, R.R. Palmer, D. Phillips, M. Spalding.
    (spring, summer):George Knoles, J.J. Johnson, D. Phillips, H.G. Warren.
  - 1948-49 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    (autumn, winter): Pacific Coast Branch (AHA), Phillip W. Buck, Claude A. Buss, T.C. Smith, R.H. Gabriel, G.H. Knoles, R. Lutz, L.C. MacKinney, C.C. Scott, Dorothea K. Thompson, A.P. Whitaker, Lottie Woods (Colonial Dames Scholarship Fund), Gordon Wright.
    (spring, summer): M. Cardozo, Merrill Jensen, J.J. Johnson, C.F. Brand, Kazuo Kawai, C. Buss, G.H. Kerr, John C. Miller, Harley Notter, T.C. Smith, A.P. Whitaker.
  - 1949-50 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    (autumn, winter): John J. Johnson, A.C./Krey, A.A. Lobanov-Rostovsky, Ralph Lutz, T.C. Smith, A.P. Whitaker, statements by staff members in reference to research activities, O.O. Winther.
    (spring, summer): Distribution of grades, L.K. Loontz, A. Lobanov-Rostovsky, microfilming of German documents, O.O. Winther.
  - 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    Claude A. Buss, C. Hodges.
  - 1957-52 (Box 2a, Folder 77a-77d)
  - 1953 (Box 2a, Folder 78)
    (winter): Alexander DeConde, Donald E. Fehrenbacher, F. Freidel, problem of chair in Japanese history.
    (spring): A. Cranston, N. Graebner, L.B. Schmidt, B.H. Swig (mentions Prof. Nasatir), J.P. Weter Scholarships.
  - 1953-54 (Box 2a, Folder 79)
    (autumn): Letter to Dean R.N. Faulkner concerning dept. business, memorandum discussing aims, functions, needs, etc. of history dept.
    (winter): Controversy over review in Pacific Historical Review of book by W. Williams, letter to Sterling on condition of library, also on D. Fahrenbacher, endowment for chair in Japanese history, J.P. Weter Scholarships, Arthur Wright.
    (spring): L.W. Dinkelspiel, E.E. Robinson, Endowed Chair in History, problems concerning assistants, Foreign Ministers' meeting in Berlin, Woodrow Wilson Foundation, graduate exams.
    (summer): Letter to Dean Acheson, Dryden Press, Gordon Craig, H.C. Jones' papers, R.R. Palmer, F.A. Shannon Gordon Wright.
  - 1954-55 (Box 3, Folder 80A)
    (autumn): Dean Acheson (with regard to Bailey's inquiry about his defense perimeter speech), C.A. Buss, A. DeConde, Franklin Hichborn, H.C. Jones (concerning his papers), A.G. Mazour, Alan Nevinx, W. Philipp, R.C. Swank, Office of Undergraduate Education.
    (winter): Jones Papers, C.B. Burdick, W.R. Coe, Anita Whitney Papers, A. Nevins, J.E.W. Sterling.
  - 1955 (Box 3, Folder 80B)
    (spring): History of the History Department, H.C. Meyer, R.C. Swank.
    (summer): Committee on Undergraduate Education, A. DeConde H. Stuart Hughes, W. Johnson, E. Pomeroy.
  - 1955 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    (autumn): History of Western Civilization (hereafter abbreviated Western Civ), D. O'Malley, W.B. Ready (library acquisitions), first inquiry about Otis Pease.
    (winter): H.S. Hughes (concerning Western Civ instructor policies), Pacific Coast Branch of AHA, correspondence concerning the coming of Prof. P. Geyl of Utrecht, E. M. Green, Thomas Hall (seeking to parsuade Hughes to come to Washington University in St. Louis), H.C. Meyer, Otis Pease, April 15 fellowship reply date.
    (spring): Letter to K.J. Arrow briefly discussing History Department research needs, K.R. Greenfield, letter to John F. Kennedy from Bailey, Otis Pease, Gordon Wright.
    (summer): F. Freidel, H.J. Tobias, Wayne Vucinich (trip to Europe and problems with Russian visa), Gordon Wright.
  - 1956-57 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    (autumn): B. Colby Papers, E. Cochrane, P. Geyl, F. Gilbert (AHA), H.K. Gunther, A. Mazour, D.M. Potter, P. Rhinelander (Dean), C.E. Schorske, requests for more money, J.W. Swain, Gordon Wright.
    (winter): F.C. Bellquist, A. DeConde, T. Edison (photos for Hoover Library), O.J. Falnes, D.H. Gabrielson (Civil War Diary of a Capt. Melhorn), J.F. Kennedy, A.R. Lewis, Coe Fund, Department self-examination (to Rhinelander), Fahrenbacher's promotion, other correspondence with Rhinelander regarding Departmental and University personal policies, problem of discussion groups in upper-division courses, R. Walker (senior colloquia), Gordon Wright.
  - 1957 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    (spring): Letters supporting J. Donohoe (Wester Civ instructor), H. Bateman (death of Prof. Wedel), W.N. Melhorn (concerning Melhorn diary), problem of office space, A. DeConde, Norman Graebner, Henry C. Meyer, P. Rhinelander (History Department business, especially personal), T.A. Bailey's correspondence with his publishers, Gordon Wright.
    (summer): C.F. Brand, H.E. Cutler, W.T. Hutchinson, R.G. O'Conner, H. Quint, Gordon Wright.
  - 1957-58 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    (autumn): J.R. Alden, William Armstrong, A. DeConde, H.H. Fisher, W.H. Kuhn, H.F. McCreery, H.C. Meyer, Bailey and his work in Washington (D.C.) on Advisory Committee on U.S. Foreign Relations, R.F. West Memorial Lectures, H. Quint, P. Rhinelander (money for teaching assistant, Western Civ), Arthur Schlesinger, Jr. D.C. Heath & Co., Fair Oaks Foundation, Foreign Campuses.
    (winter): J. Weter Scholarship, Bailey's publishers (Appleton-Century-Crofts), E.E. Lampard, R.W. Lyman, H.F. McCreery, J.C. Miller, G.B. Noble, D. Perkins, H. Quint, J. Ragland, P. Rhinelander (Department business: includes advocation for promotions for J. Johnson and Arthur Wright, material on Coe bequest and letter about H.S. Hughes), letters to J.E.W. Sterling, R.C. Swank.
  - 1958 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    (spring): H. Aitken, C.A. Barker, H.E. Cutler, A. DeConde, J. Joll, G.I. Langmuir, R. Lyman, G.B. Noble, David Potter, H. Quint, J. Raglund, P. Rhinelander.
    (summer): A. DeConde, Norman Graebner, David Harris, J. Joll, G.I. Langmuir, J.A. Monroe, G.B. Noble, H. Quint.
  - 1958 (autumn) (Box 3, Folder 86)
    H.M. Cutler Fund, A. DeConde, B.G. Noble (dealing chiefly with T.A. Bailey's work on foreign relations advisory committee), David M. Potter, P. Rhinelander, National defense training act (as regards the Ph.D. in history), letter to F.G. Terman outlining Department needs, Hispanic-America Studies, O.O. Winther.
  - 1959 (winter) (Box 3, Folder 87)
    A. DeConde, J.A. Hawgood, H.B. Melandy (concerning rumor that Stanford did not recommend best Ph.D.'s to San Jose State), history/classics major, David Potter, H. Quint, P. Rhinelander, F.D. Scott, History Department outline.
  - 1959 (Box 3, Folder 88)